Writing code is not what my job as a
software engineer is. My job is to
>> This is Dwayne Reeves. He's a senior
staff engineer or IC7 at Meta who joined
the company as a new grad from MIT.
>> Those promotions were kind of a surprise
for me because
>> he shared a bunch of lessons he learned
the hard way getting to that level.
>> I was having the worst half I ever had
at the company and I was really upset.
>> What's the story behind you becoming a
manager? You know, one of the things I
had to get used to as a manager is
>> if you could go back to yourself and
give yourself some advice, what would
you say?
Here's the full episode.
Thank you, Dwayne, for coming on. I
really appreciate your time. You know,
today I kind of wanted to go over your
career story. I feel like there's a lot
of interesting stuff because you started
at Facebook when it was Facebook and,
you know, preo and all of that. So, all
right. Well, let's start at the
beginning of your story. I see that you
started at Facebook right out of college
and you went to MIT. I'm kind of
curious. Um, were there other offers
that you were considering and what was
the story behind you joining Facebook?
>> It's actually interesting story because
I really wasn't interested in Facebook
to be honest. I was like really
interested in Google and Twitter.
Twitter because I was a big fan of Scola
as a programming language and I know
they used that as at Twitter and Google
because I grew up on the east coast and
they had offices in Boston and New York
and Facebook didn't at the time. Why I
ended up interviewing for Facebook was
actually as interview practice. I had a
friend who was working at uh Facebook
and he was trying to he joined I think
back in 2007 actually um and he was
trying to convince me throughout my time
to come for internships or other things.
I was like h I don't really know. I
don't I don't see myself going to
California and he was like finally hey
this will at least be good practice for
your Google interviews. So I was like
sure let me do it. So I did end up
interviewing and ended up making to the
final rounds and when I actually got on
campus my whole viewpoint kind of
started to change and open up. Just
being able to talk to actual engineers
and the kinds of problems they working
on. I was you know obviously a user of
Facebook being a college student at the
time and it was hard for me as someone
who is kind of interested in more core
CS problems of like oh Facebook's just a
website. What is there really for me to
do? And when I actually got on campus,
hearing like some of the problems they
had to solve with memcache and just how
to scale up a system like this, hearing
things around how they optimize PHP by
having their own custom runtime for it.
All these things made me realize like,
oh, they're actually doing some real
engineering work here. That got me
pretty interested.
>> And I mean, I imagine at Google they're
also, you know, they were obviously
doing real engineering, too. So, what
was the thing that made Facebook really
stand out?
>> Yeah. Uh, well, when is they actually
gave me an offer? But I think I think
overall the other thing is like it's
just the level of care I felt from like
they they really wanted me and they
showed it in uh sometimes not so subtle
ways. Two things that come to mind. One
was when I got my offer, it was the best
offer I had. I think I didn't I didn't
end up getting an offer from Google. I
did have an offer from Amazon. You know,
I didn't accept right off the bat
because I needed some time. I said,
"Hey, I need some time to maul over my
offer." And a week later, I got a email
out of the blue from my recruiter
saying, "Hey, we just increase your
offer."
>> I was like, "Oh, oh, wow."
>> Yeah. I was like, "Wow, I didn't even
ask for this." Versus like Amazon, I
like talked to the recruiter and they're
like, "Yeah, we don't negotiate with new
grads. You just take what you give you."
The second thing is at the time I
remember I think I had already decided
to join Facebook at that time but uh
there was something where the CTO at the
time I think Brett Taylor he actually
came to MIT's campus and took all the
new grads that were accepted and like
took us out for um like lunch like at
local cafe to like talk with us. So all
these interactions I was like wow I
couldn't imagine any seuite level person
at Google or any of the other companies
I was working at actually taking the
time to talk with us personally. So that
really spelt uh special
>> because they were smaller they're able
to do that more tailored recruiting.
What was like the rough size of the just
to give people a sense of like is this
startup or is it kind of like growth
stage or
>> Yeah, I think at the time was probably
between a,000 to,500
employees. So not small
>> but also well given we're like I think a
hundred times bigger now it's it is
small. It's all relative, right?
>> Yeah. hearing that you went to MIT, it's
not controversial to say that obviously
is a big leg up when getting uh you know
interviews and kind of you mentioned one
of your peers like had already been
working at Facebook. But one thing I'm
curious now that you have all this
experience in the industry, how much of
a correlation is there between uh maybe
the prestige of the college you went to
and a career success? I think very
little of it has to do with the actual
education piece you get at different
universities. Like my education at MIT
was fantastic. There's a lot it taught
me. I do think that's valuable,
immensely valuable. But I've also met
lots of engineers who I work with who
some of them didn't even go to school,
right? And Right. So the thing I really
know for sure was a big differentiator
between me and them was I just had more
opportunities because MIT had this name
recognition that you know for my
freshman year I was talking to
recruiters from any tech company. they
would always come to a career fair and
be willing to talk to me just because of
the school I went to versus others uh
engineers I work with is it was almost
just by chance they even got on
Facebook's radar and they were just as
capable of engineers as me but just
because of I guess a different path they
took in their career they very easily
could have not ended up at Facebook
which would have been a huge loss for
the company
>> it definitely increases the opportunity
and hands like those kinds of elements
of it.
>> Yeah. I mean, I remember my freshman
year I had an internship from Microsoft
and almost that alone was enough for me
to get a internship offer from Apple as
well. It was just kind of crazy because
I remember, you know, I grew up uh in
Bridgeport, Connecticut, growing up in
the inner city, going to public school,
you know, child of immigrants, like
working at companies like Apple or
Microsoft was like the dream. Like I
never thought real people actually work
there. Immediately going from that to oh
yeah there's recruiters here and they
actively want me to work with them was
not anything in my head I would have
even imagined being the case but MIT it
was just normal for the students there.
>> You joined Facebook, you got the offer,
they kind of you know sold you in. What
was the thinking behind joining a team
like that? When you entered Facebook,
>> we were looking at developing kind of
like a service that was meant to
evaluate some pieces of code and move it
outside of the main PHP codebase because
PHP was seen as like not a great
language to develop in. So we were like
yeah we can if we use this new language
we develop we can do some computation
closer to the data stores and all these
ideas you know this will help efficiency
and all this these big dreams. Honestly
this was something like it was not a
team on my radar at all. Um, but they
reached out to me because well maybe my
resume they thought I would be
interested and that was like I think one
of the great like first times of
actually trying to do something language
related where for the most part all I
was doing was trying to translate PHP
code into their own custom uh DSL that
they were developing. But by I was on
that team for maybe two years and by the
end of it I was actually trying to
develop new features for this language.
Ultimately that project ended up getting
cancelled. Then I started working on
more uh things related to privacy
infrastructure and how do we find ways
of representing privacy policies and
rules in a easier to manage way than
just simple if or else statements. Um
and and I did that for a couple years.
At that time, hack was introduced to the
codebase and we were kind of the newest
framework that like decided, hey, we're
gonna go all in on using hack and types,
which is what I loved because I grew up
working in statically typed languages. I
just thought they were superior. So, PHP
was always weird. Um,
and after that project, I was trying to
figure out what I wanted to do next. And
there was this opportunity of kind of
different parts of the codebase and all
that was written with PHP was not typed
in hack. And I was like I could make an
attempt at trying to type this using
hack. So it was meant to be like I think
a week or two project. It ended up
taking a whole quarter, but it was very
rewarding because it allowed me to
interact with the hack team a lot
because they're anxious of like
interested in having more people use
hack in codebase and I was trying to do
something which honestly no one else had
attempted at the time of how do we take
a very core piece of API that was not
designed to be typed and how do we
actually go about doing that and there's
a lot of hacks a lot of bash scripts a
lot of uh uh ingenuity I guess I would
say. So the end result was after I
completed this migration um about 20% of
the call sites they're moving it to the
hack API discovered that there is some
kind of error in the code usually around
how it handled null types. This was kind
of like I view as like one of the big
results of like hey hack is not just
this cool tool like it's actually
finding mistakes in the codebase at
scale and I feel that is really what
started have hack be taken a bit more
seriously is like hey should we be more
aggressive in terms of replacing PHP
with hack
>> you mentioned um you know dynamically
typed statically typed are statically
typed languages objectively better than
dynamically typed ones in industry code
It's subjective but I think a lot of
evidence points to yes they are superior
particularly in in the ways to think
about is particularly if you think about
the problems we face at a company or
codebase at the scale of we develop here
at meta or any large industry it's like
it's more of like a information
communication problem where as the size
of a code base grows the more you have
to keep your mind of the context of like
well this code is meant to do this and
this code is meant to do that. So if I
change it, this is how it needs to work.
It starts to break down as you have more
people who are working in the codebase
and the size of the codebase grows that
you just naturally need tools to help
you manage that and type systems just
happen to be a effective tool for a
communicating intent. Maybe there's
cases if you're just your hobbyist and
you're working on your own and you could
just keep everything in your own head.
Yeah, you could probably move faster
with a dynamic language at the scale we
operate with where you even if you get
like a hundred engineers like you need
something that helps you communicate
ideas and keeps track of that and that's
where I feel types really help types
also help with tooling right so you have
autocomplete it helps you search the
codebase and all these other things
beyond just like given errors that it
provides value in it's not surprising
you see even for dynamic languages most
of them have some form of optional types
at least for that reason alone.
>> I guess some of the obvious advantages
are it brings more of the the state or
what we're trying to communicate
explicitly written into the code via the
types and then also because of that
tooling and various static tools can
traverse that and provide value to us.
So that's a big value ad for industry
code. Is that right?
>> Yeah. And it's actually kind of
incredible to think about that you write
some text in a file and because you
write it in this way that we have
developed ways of proving that hey this
this text you've written does not
exhibit these classes of of errors at
all and you could just rely on it and
that's really powerful right and it's
you know one of the I think main
achievements we we've uh had in the
space of computer science
>> definitely like formally verifying that
this bug cannot happen because of those
types.
>> Exactly.
>> In my research and kind of uh you know
studying some of the the type
migrations. I think you mentioned before
like this uncanny valley of type
systems. I'm curious can you explain
what that phenomenon is and what you
mean by uncanny valley?
>> I grew up playing video games. So this
was a term I learned in that space where
from there it's from more like if you
have computer graphics as you try to
make something look more humanlike in
general you feel better about it like
you feel more connected to it as it
starts to look more human but then it
gets to a certain point where it's
almost humanlike but it's off in subtle
ways and all of a sudden you get kind of
put off from it and me being familiar
with this term I feel the same thing
will happen in terms of as you move from
dynamic languages to static languages.
And the reason I felt this way is at the
time people only worked with dynamic
languages that only fully fully
statically type languages and did not
necessarily have the muscle like memory
or like weight trained in their brain.
What does it mean if I have a type? It
actually is not correct. And as you add
more and more of these, the the places
where the types actually aren't doing
what you would expect in a static
language that exists, the more
off-putting it will feel. And so that's
how I came up with that concept, right,
was comparing this to how it applies to
the space of graphics, human human
graphics, and trying to make a similar
analogy to communicate this point. And
it proved to be really effective way of
uh contextualizing the problem we were
trying to solve on the hack team at the
time.
>> In the process of migrating to a fully
statically typed codebase, that last bit
actually things start to get worse
because you're almost there. And so the
the bugs that come are much more subtle
and the behaviors are much more subtle
and it's actually worse for a bit till
100%.
>> Yeah. And I think there's even something
particular because we were you know the
foundation of the language was PHP was
that at the time there were certain
behaviors PHP had which were
incompatible with trying to make a sound
type checker for and there were some
questions at the time of like well
should we keep those behaviors or should
we get rid of them and I think my post
was more making a statement we should
get rid of those behaviors. Because if
you have a language even if you had
everything typed the fact that the types
can't be relied upon because of these
subtle behavioral differences then that
will be a problem or will create a less
than ideal uh state for development. So
I think that's it's also some of it is
you know because of PHP and some of the
peculiar decisions they made of how
their runtime would operate.
>> I see I see that makes sense. And so in
your time as a IC, I I know eventually
you transitioned to management. So you
must have had some promotions and things
that helped your career grow. Are there
any stories like particular times where
you felt like okay that was a really
good learning experience and helped you
grow as an IC?
>> Yes, two two of them come to mind. So
one was when I got promoted yeah as a
senior engineer. I kind of mentioned
earlier about this project I worked on
of trying to create a hack API for the
for the ants framework. So since that
went well, I was asked to hey can we do
this at a at a larger scale like can we
move more code from PHP to hack? And so
I ended up spending a a half doing that.
And at that time, up to that point, my
idea of what value I gave to the company
was 100% based off of what code I was
able to output. And so when I started
this, I was talking to so many people. I
was like giving ideas to the hack team,
giving ideas to other engineers to work
on that I had almost no time to actually
write code myself. And because of this,
I felt I was having the worst half I
ever had at the company. And I remember
like having a conversation with my
manager about this. And she was like,
you know, it's important that, you know,
you're doing the right thing in terms of
talking to other people and getting them
involved, but you should find some time
to write some code on your on yourself.
And I don't know if she talked to her
her her manager afterwards, but like I
think the next one, she was like, "Yeah,
that thing I told you that's actually
wrong." Like keep on focusing on just
what the end results were. And for me
the thing that really connected still at
the end of the half I thought that I was
like yeah you know we had some results.
Yes we increased the amount of uh hack
adoption of or coverage from like I
think 20 or 30% of the code base to like
60 or 70%. Now like hack felt like it
was a fixture in the company like people
weren't really looking to write PHP
first. Everyone was starting to write
hack first. I felt like I had good
results, but again, I wrote the least
amount of code in my career so far. So,
I wasn't sure how that was going to play
out in terms of my performance review.
And the thing that really connected was
like, oh, actually, that was the highest
review I ever got. I ended up getting
redefined that half. Um,
>> wow.
>> And I got promoted to IC5, which I
wasn't even in the conversation because
I thought, oh, I'm not writing enough
code to even justify that. And it really
solidified to me that writing code is
just is not what my job as a software
engineer is. My job is to identify and
solve problems. Sometimes that's the
best way of doing that is writing code.
Sometimes it's me bringing clarity to a
problem and a path forward for how to
solve it. And if others end up writing
the code, then that's fine. Um, so
that's something I think was a pretty
big mind shift there of experience in of
like, okay, I don't have to be the most
uh efficient, you know, coded machine
out there, right? There's other ways I
could add value. So that was definitely
one of the one of the pieces. And the
second one was also, I guess, what led
to my promotion to IC6. So after that
half, right, that I just explained, I
was asked to join the hack team. So I
wasn't even on the hack team at the
time. So uh this was uh started in I
think 2015 right I joined the team uh
they said like hey you would be the tech
lead I have no idea what that was and
most of the engineers who were on the
team before they ended up leaving. So it
was like me and other engineer I brought
on the team who I worked with before and
like a new grad hire and we were like
this whole system we were now
responsible for. I quickly struggled for
a few years trying to understand what
was my role as a tech lead. You know, I
was comfortable that my output didn't
necessarily need to be related to the
code I wrote, but I still felt like I
was responsible for seeing the outcomes
and the end. So, one of the things I
worked on was trying to redesign how our
collection system work arrays and stuff
within hack. And I spent all this work
on the design, spent a whole year on it,
convinced our runtime team to implement
it. Started with the implementation and
started to roll in. We had some people
join the team and I was like, "All
right, here's my, you know, project to
get me to IC6 is trying to complete
this." And I remember my manager telling
me, "Okay, Dwayne, I actually want you
to work on something else." And I was
really upset because I was like, "What?
Why you tell me to work on something
else? This is my project is up to speed.
Why do you want me to do something
else?" and this is my path. And he was
saying like and he gave this analogy
which is really interesting. It's like
think of what you're doing is like
you're like a rocket ship and like
there's different stages as you are
firing and like you know you have the
initial set of like engines that are
meant to like leave the orbit, right?
But once you escape the orbit there's
like other jets that can fire and he was
like I only cared about you getting us
out of orbit. now that we've done that,
you should pass this off to someone
else. And now you can find something
else to do instead. And he wouldn't let
me leave the 101 until I agreed to do
it. And you know, I passed this on to
another engineer. And I was uh I don't
even remember what I was focusing on,
but I remember, you know, the half
ended. And again, I was like, "Okay,
well, I did that. So, let's talk about,
you know, what my path for six would
be." It's like, "Oh, actually, I just
got you promoted. So, uh,
congratulations. cuz you're now 06. So
in both cases, like those promotions
were kind of a surprise for me because I
had a mismatch between what my
expectations in my head of what I needed
to do to perform at the next level
versus what in reality was important.
And each time it felt like being okay
with having less direct control on the
outcome. And the real important thing I
did was just aligning what the right
strategy and what the right problems
were in the first place.
>> A lot of more senior IC's the value is
they come in they figure out what's
important to solve why you know get all
the alignment and now there's this it
kind of like the you've left orbit at
that point. This is something everyone's
interested in. Then you hand it to
someone who's great at you know getting
it done. And so it and it's cool that
your managers were uh proactive and
driving your growth because it sounds
like you weren't really eagerly involved
and figuring out, hey, what do I do to
six and you know scale myself? Okay, I'm
going to go scale myself. It's almost
like you begrudgingly did the things and
they were coaching you and you just got
promoted as a byproduct.
>> Yeah. uh you know it was also a bit
earlier at the company so some of it was
like probably they were willing to move
faster like hey Dwayne we we see the
potential in him by like hold the
promotion for another half. Having a
strong relationship with your manager is
the thing I see most consistent in like
my career. Whenever I felt disconnect
with my manager is when I felt most
frustrated. The times when I felt most
connected is when I felt I was doing my
best work. And I I think I see that that
through line in a lot of people's uh
careers. Like almost everyone who has
had success, they had a good
relationship with their manager. Um and
so speaking of management, I know you
eventually transitioned to, you know,
being a manager. Curious, what made you
want to try management? What's the story
behind you becoming a manager?
>> Uh it's interesting because it's kind of
kind of similar to how I ended up at
Facebook is like I I didn't want to be
manager. It was not a part of my career
plans. The team was at this point
growing rapidly and you know my manager
at the time he was like hey we need more
managers on the team just because of the
growth rate. Here's an opportunity for
you and we could either try and find
another manager externally or you can
give this a shot. And I said no. And the
next time I met him I heard about the
TLM role like tech lead manager and I
was like oh yeah I could do some coding
and maybe a little management. This
might be a nice transition. And I
mentioned it to my manager and he was
like, "Oh, you don't want to do this. I
was a TLM at another company. It's like
you're doing two jobs.
I wouldn't recommend this as a manager."
So I was like, "Okay, that's fine. I
won't be a manager." And I think he
probably talked to my director because
he came back the next 101. He was like,
"Actually, yeah, we should we should try
this. You could, you know, be a TLM or
whatever you want. You know, just try
this management thing." And since I, you
know, was starting to get more
comfortable with like delegating and I
was like, okay, if I'm still technically
evolved, so I could try being a manager
and still have some technical influence
on the team. And for me, the main
decision around like that point in my
career was there's so many times that
I've discovered if I was set in my way
of just trying what I felt comfortable
with that anytime I did the opposite and
did something I felt was like I would be
uncomfortable with led to better
results. So I was like, okay, I don't
really want to be a manager, but it will
force me to learn a lot and it will
force me to be uncomfortable. So I was
like, okay, I'll give it a shot. I hear
that advice often on that TLM is, you
know, two jobs and it's not super
sustainable. After you tried it, what
was your experience with being a TLM?
And would you recommend it to others?
>> The first couple years, it was actually
pretty it went pretty well. Um, as a new
manager, I was quickly, you know, I
started off with like three three
reports. I then went to four and five.
Then like there was this big shift where
essentially I had the whole team under
me. They were supposed to be a manager
in Seattle for part of her team that had
left. So I had maybe like 12 or 13
reports and I started you know saying
like all right can I convert this person
to be a manager as well? I started
having managers report to me and I was
still given technical direction. But I
think the thing that became tough was as
the org started we we were successful so
we continued to grow and became harder
and harder to think about all right how
can I continue to contribute as a tech
lead while also figuring out how to
scale out this Oric. And there was, you
know, some ideas I had around how to do
it, which was basically I need few of
reports. Let me get like three managers
to do all the management and I'll just
manage them. Then I have time to think
as a tech lead. You know, my own manager
at the time, he didn't think that was
the best outcome as for building a
healthy org, which I think makes sense
because he has a lot more experience
being an org leader. Ultimately, I got
scaled down to here's a fewer direct
IC's I worked with and I continued being
the tech lead overall. So, it wasn't
necessarily the workload that was the
issue, but it became something where
does the thing that helps the team the
most align with the base
responsibilities I need to do as a
manager. So, here's a way to kind of
demonstrate this, right? So as a tech
lead at the time I think there was
something like 35 to 40 individuals on
the larger team that we were working
with our on the language team and so the
best thing for that 35 to 40 group of
individuals of what I should do is
different versus the maybe six or seven
IC's I was directly supporting and so I
had a PSC where if I would be graded as
a IC I was told I would get a GE like
basically my role as a tech lead for
this group of 35 to 40 individuals I was
doing really great at. But as a manager,
I wasn't failing. I was a good manager,
but I had to do do that job
successfully. I I wasn't necessarily
looking to exceed as a manager or do or
maximize the growth of those six to
seven individuals I was supporting
directly. And this became something is
like is this actually what's best for
the team long term? And ultimately I had
a choice of I could basically try to
replace myself as a tech lead so I could
focus on being a org manager or go back
to being an IC so I could focus more
freely my time on what the needs of the
larger organization needed from
technical leadership. And the choice
became obvious for me as like it was
just easier to find a manager for six to
seven people than me trying to find
someone who can be effective tech lead
for a group. So that's what ended what
led me back to being an IC.
>> You mentioned that in along that journey
you managed some EM and you managed IC's
as well. I'm kind of curious what's the
difference between managing an IC and
EM?
>> It's really the difference between
trying to support someone as they are
working through technical problems
versus people problems. You know, one of
the things I had to get used to as a
manager is, you know, when you're IC or
you're doing something technically, the
feedback loop between you doing an
action versus you seeing the results of
that action is shorter versus what you
try to do as a manager, right? So if I'm
working with a IC, I'm trying to uplevel
them so they could take on larger bits
of work or learn how to be more creative
or thorough in terms of the work that
they do. As a manager, the things I
attempt to do in one meeting, one
oneonone, I have no idea if it helps,
right? There isn't something I could
tell like, oh, I hit compile and then I
it passed or I run the unit test and now
it passed. But as a uh manager, like it
might be like six months, nine months
down the line where like something
clicks or they come to a meeting or
oneonone and say, "Hey, I finally got
that thing you said and I'm actually
seeing results from it." Now that same
thing applied to uh pe a people manager
is even like a longer loop I'll say of
like the problems they have of like and
some of it was I was a new manager so I
wasn't always necessarily clear around
like well what's the best ways of
getting them the things they were
struggling with as a manager what advice
can I give them how can I coach them up
it wasn't something that I actively went
in it's like I need to do something
different for these managers, right? I
was kind of a vibe manager. I was just
like, "This feels like the right thing."
And I think for the most part, things
were fine, right? From a standpoint, the
team, the org was doing well, but I
wasn't necessarily focused on optimizing
the org. I was like, "Fine, if the org
just ran, right, and I was able to do
technical work." So um you know I know
you asked about what's the difference
between the IC and the manager in terms
of management. It was more like for me I
was realizing my brain was focused more
as like still as a IC is like the or is
fine for the most part. I'm not looking
for other opportunities to see this
organization operate more. And those are
the kinds of stuff I think you should be
thinking more about as you are more of
an org lead and are supporting other
managers is helping them think about as
they have their own team like how they
should coach others or how what
opportunities they should be thinking
about or even seeing like does it even
make sense for them to be a manager
still or should I or is there some other
opportunities. So, these are the types
of stuff I probably should have been
doing more of as a as a skip manager.
You know, I think I think the thing I
enjoyed the most around management
though was around the coaching. And so,
that's what I leaned on a lot more was
like oneonone was like, "What's your
problems? How can I help?"
>> And it sounds like the coaching that you
enjoyed most was IC coaching because you
liked being an IC yourself. So, and
you're saying that for EM reporting to
you, the best thing is to kind of flip
that switch and start thinking about the
best org design and how do we grow
people and how are they going to support
their team.
>> Yeah. And that just wasn't the natural
way I was thinking like daytoday
particularly because yeah, I was the
tech lead. So if I came in 80% of my day
focused on what's the technical
challenges we have and how can we best
cha tackle them trying to switch to 20%
of my brain of like well is this even
the right structure we have to best
execute on this plan. I I just was not
good at switching between the two.
>> Yeah. At some point you're promoted to
senior staff or IC7 equivalent. I'm
curious what's the story behind the
promotion? So we talked earlier about
this uncanny valley like post and that
was really that vision was what drove
the team for a while like as we started
to scale up the size of the team and
what we were pursuing a lot if you ask
anyone in the team what were we doing it
was like oh we're trying to cross the
uncanny valley and I think what led to
the promo was basically enough things
lined up as we were executing and we
were making progress towards this that
was like attributable to my vision that
it made sense to be promoted right at
that point. It was something I remember
being a bit more active talking to my
manager about and at that point in time
it was kind of seeing as like it's just
a matter of time. We just need to see
more like results because I had a clear
vision I had laid out and we were
starting to see results from it. So, we
just needed to see it a little bit
further along before we got the
promotion through. And yeah, I ended up
getting it the half before I switched
back to being the IC. So, I was actually
still a manager when I got promoted. I
think at the time they said officially
TLMs didn't start until M2 equivalent.
So, if you're at M1 and you're a tech
lead manager, like no, you're just a
manager, right? But I think the promo to
M2 was based on the technical
contributions I gave as more IC as
opposed to my ability as or lead.
>> If I'm understanding the the blast
radius of what you' done was basically a
migration of the full to fully
statically typed on one of the base I
guess languages that almost everyone was
using. I don't know the exact
percentages but you know hundreds at
least maybe even thousands of engineers
using this. Is that right?
>> Yeah. I joined the team in 2015.
We had a mix of some hack and some PHP
and we soon moved to basically
everything being hack. We also had some
notion of like hack strict mode versus a
partial mode where strict had
requirements that you wrote all the
types that were necessary versus partial
you could leave things out or whatever.
And by this time I got promoted we
basically got all the codebase. So back
in 2015, out of the hack files which
were in the codebase, maybe only like
five or 10% were strict. So by the end
of this, right around the time where I
got promoted, we more or less had all of
the codebase now being strict hack. And
so that was like a pretty remarkable
difference, you know, plus a bunch of
other work we did of uh changes to the
language runtime and other things that
had kind of paid off at that point.
Coming to the end, there's uh I kind of
want to go over like some career
reflections going over the story. One
thing that I was curious about is
because you're early at Facebook, you've
probably had a lot of chance to work
with some uh very legendary IC's. I'm
curious, is there any IC that you worked
with or you thought uh you were really
impressed by them or maybe you have a
story working with someone?
>> Oh, yeah. Oh, there's so many excellent
IC's I' I've worked with. So, I almost
feel a miss if I call some out, but I'll
I'll mention one. Uh Kendall Hopkins, I
worked with him when he first joined the
company and um he's an excellent IC who
was really good at understanding for a
codebase um or main, you know, our main
codebase that was running hack. I was
thinking from a language perspective. He
was thinking in more from the developer
perspective like what are they actually
trying to do like what are products
needs like what do product engineers
need within this codebase and he's just
was an excellent engineer in helping to
think and strategize like how do we make
these larger changes at scale across the
codebase. So he was very key I think
instrumental in my success. Uh another
one that comes to mind was Paul Biznet.
You know, I don't know if I said this
explicitly, but when I joined hack, I
had no prior experience with languages
or compilers or anything. Honestly, I
didn't even know what Alexa was, which
is like a very base component of a
parser. And Paul, he answered, he was my
sounding board. Like, I could ask him
anything and I felt comfortable. No
matter how dumb it was, he would take
the time to explain it. And so I don't
think I would have survived particularly
when talking with the HHVM team if I
didn't have Paul there to kind of um
teach me different concepts. Yeah. And
another one I just want to call out is
you know he's still a colleague of mine
Andrew Kennedy. Uh this guy is
incredible. He's literally written
foundational papers on type theory. like
you would do some research like let me
look up some things around type theory
and you're like oh Andrew Kennedy his
name is here and he and he kind of
figured this out and um it was one of
those cases I did not when I first met
him I did not know how amazing or his
pedigree that he had and he's one of the
most humblest guys I I've met for
someone who's so accomplished already
working with him has really showed that
I shouldn't be afraid of um someone's
prestige like I have value to add even
if it seems like I'm not you know you
know I'm more junior or anything else
right that there's always something
everyone has their strengths and there's
something you could always add to that
and uh with Andrew there are times where
talk about different language features
or ways of typing and even though I
didn't have the same background he had
finding ways where we can communicate
and see like he would say oh Dwayne
that's actually interesting viewpoint I
hadn't thought about that made me feel
like hey I could actually you know punch
and hold my weight. And then there's
stuff he'll do. I'm like, I had no idea
like how to even think about this
problem. So, yeah, those are just some
of the some of the IC's I I really call
out is like uh me having worked a lot
with and seeing just some of the amazing
work they've done at the company. It
sounds like it was humanizing working
with him because you I mean I guess if
you had just heard about him, you'd
think this guy's untouchable, but
getting to work with him, seeing him be
friendly, adding value and discussions
kind of made it so that you were uh I
guess not scared of his prede. Is that
right?
>> Yeah. And that's something for myself,
you know, having, you know, been on Hack
now for 10 years and been at the company
for almost 14. It's something I'm
sensitive to as well because I still
remember that time when I was just a
younger engineer. And so every once in a
while, I'll go I'll meet someone and
I'll introduce myself and they're like,
"Wait, you you're the Dwayne? Like
you're like the hack guy?" And I'd be
like, "Oh, like, oh, don't think of me
like that." You know, I I want to be
approachable. I want people's ideas to
feel valued. And, you know, yeah, we're
all humans. We all learn things, right?
And just because of whatever I've
accomplished in the past or any ideas I
have doesn't mean I'm always right. I'm
always looking to learn more. And I
think that's one of the things was great
around the team I had was just so many
senior IC's, those with, you know, some
I talked to had more experience working
on programming languages than I was
alive at the time, but yet
>> that's crazy.
>> Yet how willing they were to talk to me
and and explain their their approach.
And I just think that's something all
all senior IC should try to emulate that
like humility.
>> You mentioned you've been at the company
for a long time. I'm curious like what
is the thing that you find keeps you at
meta? I think in this industry a lot of
people you know hop jobs.
>> Yeah. So there are definitely some times
I think of where and I was considering
jumping ship and the thing that I always
reflect on right is is my motivation for
moving is it trying to solve a temporary
problem? So let's say like, hey, at the
time I'm not particularly happy with the
project I'm working on. Is that really a
reason for me to leave the company,
right? And versus like um and each time
I you know I would interview and I would
have an offer and I would think like is
me making this change or move really
going to change like the fundamental
problem I feel I have at the moment? And
each time I reached that that point, I
would just objectively look at well what
are the problems I have and what are
also the things I enjoyed about the work
I did and particularly growing up at
this company you know things that I was
being I had a voice that would had
carried weight. I had opportunities to
help bring in diverse talent into the
company and frankly how many
opportunities is there to work on a on a
programming language? I was that was
also the piece and I had a great team
and so if there was a moment of like
yeah there's some discomfort that was
for like two months is that really worth
changing over right and for me I always
was like yeah I could I could sit
through it and most of the time things
ended up improving uh and so that was
for me my like perspective is that I
don't want to make permanent decisions
based off of temporary circumstances.
>> And it sounds like I guess in those
cases when it wasn't good, the situation
was resolvable. It was not something
that you couldn't change or your manager
couldn't help you with.
>> Yeah. You know, I feel some of the
things in terms of what would lead what
would have led me to like leave, right,
is if I didn't feel valued. And in a lot
of cases, I when I would look at like
no, there's all the signs that I I am
valued here at this place. And so the
issues was not focused on that. It was
like something else like oh it's a it's
a project I'm working on. Do I feel it's
not getting the recognition it deserves?
And some of it realistically might be
like I just have a war view of what I
think should be recognized and if I talk
and really face this like yeah I'm
actually wrong here or maybe they are
wrong and me with enough time they
realize that you know if I fundamentally
did not believe in the mission of the
company or like I felt my manager was
creating a toxic work environment things
like that would be more of what I would
see is like yeah if I'm in that
situation I would have left already. But
none of those were like the
circumstances I had. And honestly, I
feel I'm a bit privileged and fortunate
of that to experience that in my career.
And it's it leads to a lot of like
there's just been so many great people
in my time. I've been able to work with
both managers and others at the company
that it's let me really have a career so
far that like goes beyond my wireless
dreams. Right. When I was first learning
to code as a high school student, you
know, the child of Jamaican immigrants,
I would have never in my wildest dreams
have thought that I would have end up
with the opportunities I've had working
at this company. And it's not I don't
want to say sentimental, but it's really
appreciating that like I've actually
been really blessed and really
fortunate. And I guess the last question
I want to ask you is now that you have
all this experience, if you could go
back to yourself right when you
graduated college and give yourself some
advice, what would you say?
>> I get asked this often and the thing is
the thing I'll say is, "Hey Dwayne, I
know you like coding, but the thing you
should realize, right, is when someone
goes and tells you, hey, can you write
some code to do this?" You should stop
and think, how do they know that's the
right code to to write? You should aim
to be the person who's making those
decisions around what's the right thing
to do. There's a lot of imposttor
syndrome and other stuff I dealt with
early in my career that having this
clarity is like it's not about you know
I'm more than what I can type on the
keyboard right my ideas and the value I
derive is is greater and like focus not
on just being an output machine but
really being the one and focus like can
I be in those rooms that's deciding
what's the right thing to do. Yeah,
thanks for sharing. And I I feel like
someone with your amount of career
success sharing that you had imposter
syndrome, I think that can be helpful
for a lot of people. So, um, yeah, thank
you so much for your time, Dwayne. I
really appreciate you coming on.
>> Yes, it was a pleasure, Ryan. Thank you
so much.
>> Hey, thanks for watching the show. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to support, you can
subscribe on YouTube or you can leave a
review on Spotify. And I'm always
looking for new guests to interview. So,
if anyone comes up who you think you
really want to hear their career story,
uh, let me know and I'll try to reach
out to them and get them on the show.
Thanks for listening as always and I'll
see you next time.